我哋今次嘅。
監察西九文化區計劃，誒嘅。
聯合小組委員會會議。
噉我哋首先咧就請呢個誒。
世界管理局同埋政府嘅代表進入。
好嘛？
噉啊！出席嘅政府人員同埋西九管理局嘅人員咧，都喺。
誒，大家嘅。
以前嘅文件嘅裏邊。
歡歡迎大家。
我哋今日咧就兩個議程，誒。
就去去到一點鐘嚇，噉啊，以前第一項咧就係Amicus嘅發展最新嘅進展，噉啊，之前文件已經係。
交誒畀咗大家，噉我哋咧就先請政府。
誒嘅代表或者西九嘅代表簡介呢個文件誒，同埋利用嗰個投影片係同大家説明，係嘛邊位先？
Mr. Lynch, please. Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Members of the committee. Oh, something's gone wrong. Here we are.
Today, I think is a really important part of us being able to make clear to the committee what an absolutely integral part M Plus is of the West Kalimantan Cultural District, and also very important in that it sits in the park end of the project.
unaffected by any of the issues related to the railway or the basement, it will be one of the first venues open to the public, and it will be very important in terms of its relationship to the broad audience.
We've made some, I think, very significant progress over the past year in the development of M Plus, including the building of a team, the building of the collection, building the museum building, as well as raising public awareness awareness through a number of the inventive pre-opening programmes that we've undertaken.
including inflation, the M+ building exhibition, and in particular the joint collaboration with the Arts Development Council of responsibility, the
for the last Venice Biennale with the artist Lee Kit, and the recently announced collaboration with the ADC for the next Venice Biennale next year.
I think one of the issues that we're very aware of is that M Plus is a new type of museum of contemporary visual culture, unlike anything seen in Hong Kong before. Particularly in the not-for-profit sector, we realise it takes time and a very conscious effort to educate and communicate.
to the public what a visual culture museum is and how such a museum works. This is not an easy task, but it is definitely a very important part of the journey that we would go through going forward. I'm very pleased today to be able to have the M+ director Lars Netter.
Who's led the team and built the team so that we now have some forty-eight people now working on the development of the museum, the development of the collection. I think we're doing a pretty good job in terms of moving it forward on a lot of fronts, and that's.
Clearly one of the challenges of this project, and no, I think we're bringing no the best practice from all over the world to ensure that M Plus will be a museum that Hong Kong is rightly proud of. And I'm now going to hand over to Dr Nitfa to bring.
bring you up to date on all of the aspects, including the building part of the project and any of the areas that you may want to question us specifically on. Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Okay.
有冇政府有冇補充？其他人。
啊。
唔使理。
主席，和謝謝Michael Nulsen for this introduction。
嗯。
Well, some of you may have been on this committee for.
三、年或更多，和我，是第四次，我有榮幸坐喺度報告M+嘅發展。和，總體上，我必須話，一切喺按計劃、時機，和，其實無任何重大。
Hiccups, which is is quite wonderful to be able to report. I've always said that we're basically doing four things. We are building a team that develops ideas, etc., etc. And from these ideas, you then start building a collection, which we have come quite far with. And once the collection
Sort of is taking shape. We start developing the ideas of what sort of building do we need for the collection, and then the fourth strand is of course to develop audiences and the relationship with audiences. And this is what we've been doing for the last three, three and a half years. For the period, there's been a team on board, and we continue.
在過去幾年，The District、WKDA和M+ has made significant progress in a number of areas，包括collection and acquisition、museum facilities、governance structure、capacity building、audience building，以及 stakeholder engagement。我會講。
講 to you about these things.
When it comes to the collection.
Just to look at some some figures around it, as of June 30th of June 2014, M Plus has acquired. And here I exclude the major acquisition through purchase and mainly donation from of the M Plus Sig collection. We have acquired.
Around 920 works. On top of that, in terms of value, geographical distribution of these acquisitions, it's quite balanced in terms of its relationship between Hong Kong, China, other parts of Asia, Chinese diaspora, and overseas.
Beyond Asia.
And if you look at the number of works from Hong Kong, it's a bit over 50% of the total number of works purchased since 2012, when we started making the acquisitions. It's not yet two years ago when the acquisition process started.
The roadmaps and these are really the sort of the maps that define the directions to go, the order to take things, where to go first, and sort of strategies for acquisition. The roadmaps for
different collection areas.
such as Incart for example, design the Greater Asia collection have been presented to the interim acquisition committee already last year, and M Plus is currently conducting an in-depth research and developing the strategy for the Hong Kong visual culture and.
Sort of deepen strategy, I should say. There is already a strategy in place, and for moving image, and the latter actually the roadmap for that was presented as late as yesterday to the interim acquisition committee.
這個委員會 held seven meetings during the financial year of 2013-14, and looking at the period from the 1st of April 2013 until the 30th of June, so very recently, 2014, acquisitions by purchase total.
was totalling 352 works of visual culture, so clearly it's not only art, it's design, it's architecture, it's moving image material as well. That's important to remember, and out of these 79 were from Hong Kong.
Now, I think something that is.
Often forgotten and not commented on much, but which is quite remarkable and a sign of extraordinary support for the M+ project is the interest M+ has attracted from major artists, collectors.
建築師和設計師， who have made various important donations， including， for example， the generous donation of 37 important works of Chinese contemporary art， mainly installations， very substantial installations， from Mr. Guan Yi， who is one of the most important art collectors in China。
係啊！
The donation also, I should mention the donation of work, the work "Guards Kissing" by Tino Segal, who is one of the major international artists at the time, from Mr. Alan Lau, who is an avid collector of contemporary art here in Hong Kong.
We had quite extraordinary anonymous donation to support the acquisition of Asian Field by Anthony Gouramly.
And we had recently a cash donation, which has been written about quite a bit in the newspaper, in the name of the Brown Family Annual Acquisition Fund for acquiring artworks at Art Basel Hong Kong in the coming ten years.
所以，至6月30日2014年，M+已收到2,029件藝術品及其他設計、建築、動畫作品，來自51個不同的捐贈者：藝術家、香港藝術家、海外藝術家、收藏家、建築師。
designers and so forth.
和，作為兩項捐款，現金捐款，總值約港幣一億元。
三百五十萬，三百五十千香港 dollars。
and I should say that in the same period of time we have made purchases for about 325 million Hong Kong dollars, so we have received donations of a value of more than 1 billion more than we have purchased for, and I think that's worth noting.
Of course, we will continue our effort in securing more donations, and there are very good signs that we will get those. And actually, we had an informal confirmation of a large cash donation yesterday.
但係，太早要公佈詳細。
為強化其對透明度的承諾，WKSDA已公佈M+購入政策，該政策是根據美國、加拿大及澳洲等主要博物館的政策發展而成，並在與獨立委員會的諮詢下制定。
against corruption.
The approving procedures and limits are laid down in the policy, and they are comparable to those of many major international museums. As a matter of fact, both the policy and and the
The procedures are, I would say, more extensive and firmer than in most international museums. For instance, M+ needs to seek approval from the WKSDA board before making major acquisitions, and then, depending on the price value of the proposed acquisition, the M+
政策設出不同買進批准機構，由成員具強藝術及文化背景。我認為這非常重要，即係買進決定由具知識的人作出，唔係交畀唔識呢個領域的人。
In addition, the complete list of the M Plus Sig collection, as well as other recent acquisitions and donations, have been uploaded on the WKDA official website for public information.
誒。
要過到博物館建築，你可能記得，4M+，它是個重要的提醒，總是要説，博物館不能和建築混淆，博物館是內容和它和觀眾的關係，建築。
Building is a tool for this relationship. It's a tool to bridge the gap, to create this meeting between the content, the artworks, the design works, the the architecture models and
和公眾，但係佢唔係同博物館一樣。所以喺某種程度上，你可以話M+存在作為博物館已經，因為除咗建築之外，其他嘢都係準備好，可以同中型博物館相對比。我們有優秀嘅團隊，有成長嘅藏品，有展覽計劃。
We have relationship to our audiences on a very regular basis, just like museums do. The museum, the building is missing. I'd like though to say a few words about the building because it is important and it is a big investment as well, and it is moving forward very well.
作為成員們可能記住，得獎設計為M+建築。
was well the the design competition to start with was won about a year ago by the Swiss architect firm Herzog and de Meuron in in joint venture with Hong Kong based TFP Farrells and Over Arab and Partners Hong Kong and it's called the HDM joint venture.
係。
They were selected from a shortlist of an international competition, of which with six of the world's leading architecture firms participated. Five of which at the present have won the Pritzker Prize, the equivalent of the Nobel Prize for an architect. So it was from quite an extraordinary team.
They were selected.
The winning design for the M+ building is, and I will show some images, is made up of basically two slabs.
一個水平的 slab。
和垂直 slab slab 是一個醜陋的詞，其實，但但，pieces of a building。
And in general, you can say that the horizontal slab has a number of functions. It starts underground already, and where you have public facilities, you have an entrance from the park. You come to the extraordinary space called the found space, which is actually.
作為一個挖掘的機場快線隧道，給我們一個驚人的和不尋常的地下空間。但同時，它也容納了，例如，動態影像中心，這是一個完全獨特的博物館方面。
呃，你可以 entry 已經直接從公園，從公園。我諗我先揀啲好嘛，因為留畀啲時間畀啲同事問問題。
OK， next floor is a public plaza for the for the public and that's the main entrance floor. But also with education facilities. And the next floor is the main exhibition space. The vertical part has the research centre, library, archive accessible to the public.
It has a coratorial research centre. It has and it has three floors on the top that are restaurants for RDE simply. And this building, because there were questions about this, there has been earlier on, is.
The conservation storage facility, which is actually part of the same building, and it's attached underground to the museum and houses our storage with thousands of works and also the conservation facilities.
this is another view from the sea showing highlight I can highlight here the education centre which is an extraordinary feature in the building and of course you can also see the wonderful large roof terrace which has public access it's actually open public space.
And yet another view that shows the sort of easy access, openness into the building, which is from the Artis Square into the into the museum building, and how easily accessed it is.
Moving on.
我應該説，那The M+ Design Consultancy Services commenced in September 2013，所以係about 10 months ago。Detail design，We've gone through conceptual design or schematic design，and is detail design is progressing well，and is due to
for completion in December 2014.
Now, as the Finance Committee of the Legislative Council has not been able to consider the funding application of the advanced public infrastructure works in the M+ portion of the integrated basement as scheduled for July 2014, for last week.
It is anticipated, unfortunately, I must say, that the completion date, the OP for M+ will be revised from the end of 17 to the first half of 2018.
同時，則，進度工程於2014年4月1日開始，預計於2014年8月完成。
also in keeping with WKSD's prudent financial management, regular reviews are being undertaken to monitor the estimated construction cost. Value engineering studies etc. etc. has constantly been going on and will continue to form a part of the ongoing design management and cost control activity.
And at the present, but of course that is just at the present, we are according to the quantitative surveyors on budget.
誒。
另一個重要 aspect 是 governance structure。
Following the recommendations of the consultative committee of the core arts and culture facilities of the WKDA, as well as the report to them from the museum advisory group in 2006, WKDA has studied the governance structure of major museums overseas to consider how the.
Future M+ should be managed.
為目的，消除法律歧義在公眾眼中的公共處理博物館，行政透明度、可追蹤性和效率，以及最大化公眾對藝術自由和館藏獨立性的認知。M+的治理。
會被 implemented 通過設立一個 wholly owned 子公司 under WKD 為一個獨立的法律實體。
Under the WKSDA, I should underline.
under this model, the WKSDEL board will be the body setting overall policies for the governance of WKSDE, including M+。
和總體戰略方向 for the WKSDA，而新M+ 董事會 for the wholly owned subsidiary 將發展 mandate、 mission、 vision 和運作策略 for M+。
M+ would retain control over its museological and curatorial policies, and the M+ board would hold the authority to approve the daily work and decisions within defined levels.
this would allow for more effective and streamlined operations of the museum.
M+管理及 governance need to be compliant with the policies of WKSDA.
And WKD is currently working out further details to implement the governance structure.
Capacity building, of course, building the team has been a central and a totally essential aspect of of creating M Plus, and we have gradually been building up our professional expertise in different areas, including of course curatorial practice, collection management, art education.
Research and technical areas, especially the back of house areas.
目前，的招聘重點在於館藏管理及典藏管理領域。這是為了確保M+擁有足夠的典藏管理專業知識，以及在四大主要視覺文化領域的專業知識，以及管理不斷擴大的M+典藏。
The focus will also slowly shift towards the areas of audience development, digital programme, publications, membership and building management. M+ currently has a total of actually we're around moving rapidly towards 40 members of staff, with 18 in the curatorial area, actually 19 as of yesterday.
六在收集管理，一在建築區，和餘下都是執行或行政職務。
and of the now 19 curatorial staff, 10 are actually young curators from Hong Kong. They're not the only curators from Hong Kong, but that shows that.
It's really possible to recruit young, talented, well-educated, but maybe in some cases unexperienced curators in Hong Kong who can grow in the organisation. Well.
Internship. I thought you were interested in this internship and volunteer programmes to meet the increased demand for artistic and administrative talents, as well as curatorial, art education and back of house staff. Mプラス has launched different internship and volunteer programmes. All in all, I've.
We've had around 20 interns over time, and some of them are now coming into the team also. And the docent volunteer programme was launched last year. We had about 800 applications for it. We have at the current 47 who are in an education programme with us, and it's anticipated.
that it will continue in the coming years.
Audience building, of course, the main strategy for building audiences is really by having a public programme, by showing, by having people participate. And the main vehicle there are the exhibitions we make, the mobile and plus exhibitions, and the exhibition as we did last year in Venice.
Where we organised together with ADC the presentation of Venice artist Lee Kit and the exhibition UU, which had an extraordinarily good reception in Venice and internationally.
一個展覽，後來在擴大版到香港，以《U》為題。
在 cattle depot，其他 exhibitions that have been hugely successful is building M plus the museum and architecture collection， which presented the architecture competition where we are at this stage in the design of the M plus building and also our growing architecture collection。
And it was an exhibition that attracted more than 20,000 visitors out in Artis Tree.
其他展覽是，如我所提，的《烈焰》展覽和《Mobile N Plus Neon Signs HK》，這是一個互動線上展覽，專門探討、繪製及記錄香港的霓虹燈。由於有關於霓虹燈位置的質疑，
落區。
went in our programme. This is a good example how we work with popular culture.
誒，要評估最後一分鐘啊。
One minute, well, it's up to you.
We have ADC has come back and said that they invite us to do the next.
展覽在威尼斯，作為與他們合作，MPlus已接受邀請，並於6月26日發布新聞稿，藝術家已於10天前宣佈，是從香港來的，當然。
We also did a very successful exhibition at Hong Kong Art Basel, and on top of that, I can report about M Plus Matches, very very successful, always sold out programmes of public talks and workshops, and finally stakeholder engagement.
where we regularly do the public forums that are also very popular and well well visited, where we update the public in a similar way as we've done now, but at greater length about how the project is developing. Thank you, Chairman.好多謝你啊！你已經用咗廿五分鐘講咗㗎啦，嚇嚇。
咁而家咧誒？
報名嘅咧就係有誒黃碧雲、姚思榮誒副主席誒陳婉霞，就何秀蘭同埋毛孟靜誒，我會最後，每人四分鐘連問連答，掌握時間。我哋呢個呢節咧會十二點鐘結束，係十一點十結束嚇。
誒，多謝主席。我想問下咧，就兩方面嘅問題啦。第一個咧就係誒，關於Amphas嘅誒博物館啦，嗯。
呢度提到咧，我哋好希望佢係有一個香港嘅角度嘅，係有一個香港嘅特色嘅。
係會有香港嘅視覺文化同埋流動影像嘅。
咁咧就關於第五點嗰度，即係呢一個香港嘅視覺文化同埋流動影像。嗱，我哋希望咧呢個empas咧唔係一個即係好似我哋去旅行去其他國家睇人哋嘅大型嘅博物館噉。即係呢啲我哋去旅行，即係啲市民都會出去出邊啦。我哋唔希望我哋翻到嚟empas咧，又好似去咗旅行。
根本。
睇一啲咧係冇一個本地嘅特色，我哋好希望佢係有嗰個獨特本地嘅獨特性。一睇嘅時候，香港市民入去覺得呢個係我哋嘅。
一個visual culture係我哋嘅視覺文化，係我哋香港嘅本土藝術，所以呢個本土性。
嗰個local visual culture、local visual history呢啲咧，我好希望喺呢一個策展或者你喺收購一啲嘅物品嘅時候咧，係一定要突出佢。
如果唔係呢個就唔係我哋香港人嘅一個emphasis，而係一個我哋將一個外國嘅舶來品擠喺本地。噉我希望你哋喺成個構思裏邊係令到香港人係會有共鳴嘅。咁所以呢一度咧，我想問啊，就係好多人咧形容香港係一個示威遊行之都，因為每年一月一號、六月四號、七月一號。
跟住唔知十十月一號嚇，唔知啊。總總之，好多大大型嘅、大型嘅。
動員示威，無論邊個搞都好，呢啲都係香港好重要嘅一個誒文化、本地文化特色，或者嗰個視覺文化特色。呢啲相關嘅照片啦、影像啦，有冇展開一個計劃收購，或者係誒？
呼籲啲N.G.O嚇佢哋係捐出有關嘅物品，然後會有一個噉樣嘅展館咧。咁即係呢個係第一個問題。第二個咧就係關於嗰個嘅誒第十六段嗰個governance十五十六。
咁誒，將來咧就而家講緊咧，就係話喺西九管理局底下咧，會有一個全資附屬嘅誒公司去睇住Ample嘅，而呢度亦都會有一個Ample嘅董事局。咁但係呢度完全冇提到個董事局咧，係將會有幾多人啦，嗰個組成會係點啦，嗰個representation。
會係點啦？有幾多即係好熟悉香港culture嘅人係會喺呢一度啦？咁因為咧呢度你講到咧新嘅Amper董事局咧係要負責制定佢嘅目標、使命、願景同埋營運策略，即係我就好擔心嘅，因為你呢度冇組成，然後又話交畀佢。
去定Amper嘅目標、使命同願景。
即係具體營運策略，當當然佢哋可以慢慢傾。但係呢啲咁大嘅目標願景，唔係應該我哋已經大家即係喺呢一度都應該要傾清楚，或者西九管理局應該已經係有個好清楚嘅指示咩？定係仲要交畀一個新生出嚟嘅董事局，而佢可以？
佢係諗一啲咩嘢？佢係可以會同西九管理公唔一致嘅咩？係冇可能㗎嘛？係嘛？嚇，可唔可以講一講嗰呢兩個問題？O.K.誒，邊位精簡啲嘅回答？
嗰個問題。
Mr. Lynch， or else。
好，多啲。
So, yeah, no, I'm happy to answer. To start with, of course, I completely agree that M+ should not be like any museum overseas. It should definitely be unique to Hong Kong, and there's no point in creating it otherwise. And actually, people would have no reason to go there from overseas even.
If if it's the same as they can get anywhere else, so clearly it's meant to reflect Hong Kong, but also and that's the distinction that I think we're developing together with the Hong Kong Museum of Art and Heritage Museum. We have an international perspective. We look at the world also from a
Hong Kong perspective, but it will be totally rooted in Hong Kong. And of course, but it's not only. And that was outlined already in the museum advisory group's paper in 2006. It's not only a museum about Hong Kong because we have two museums, major museums, that do that. But definitely, and everyone I think who's seen what we've done, read about what.
We're doing, read our books and so forth. It's clear, I think, are convinced that this is really rooted in Hong Kong. So I totally agree with your your point there.
在terms of documentary material，實際上國際或臨時買進委員會在討論關於路線圖的動畫影像資料時，有一個被提出來的東西，就是紀錄片。紀錄片是其中一個成員在。
The committee is Nancy Shi, who is well known to us all, I think, and she really encouraged also the inclusion of important documentary material and documentary films into the moving image scenarios. So it's not only about movies or or just about. It's really a wide area, and we should look.
the whole wide area, while of course remembering that the quality of the work, the height of the of the work is there. We're not a cultural, what shall I say, a general cultural history museum. We are of course.你睇下我我仲啱先答啦，好嘛，Mr. Ah，姚思榮。
誒都想問下文件嘅第十一段嘅，就係講因為立法會嗰個財務委員會嗰個審批未能完誒如期咁處理啦，咁所以咧Amicus嗰個員工嘅日期咧會推遲半年到嚇。咁講真，而家都唔知幾。
幾時會批出嚟？噉我唔知道誒。
佢哋嗰嗰邊咧，會唔會考慮即係有冇一個估計啊？每次一個月撥款嘅話咧，嗰個開支會增加幾多嚇？咁如果增加呢筆費用咧，佢哋點樣去安排呢筆預算咧？咁呢個第一個問題。
第二個就係關拓展呢個觀眾羣嘅問題。
噉啊，我哋睇到咧，而家Amperis已經係開始誒有啲流動嘅展覽平台喺誒唔同嘅地方展覽啦，亦參加唔同嘅一啲誒誒海外嘅展覽都有嘅。噉我想問下就係話，咁耐咧一共有幾多嘅？
觀眾係參加呢啲噉嘅活動。
誒，其中咧本地觀眾同埋海外嘅觀眾嘅比例係幾多啊？噉啊，根據誒。
而家攞到個數字咧，未來誒Amperes本身佢哋對海外觀眾嗰方面有咩嘢誒考慮同埋推廣計劃咧？噉樣兩個問題。
O.K.
明白。And I'll take the first one. Clearly, clearly we are in regard to the delay issues. The issues of delays in consideration by the public infrastructure committee is incredibly important, not just to M+, but to all of the other parts of this project. And clearly, we are anxious that those
決 decisions expedited as soon as is possible. At this point, we cannot be definitive, as you said. We don't know when, as you don't know when those decisions are going to be made. But clearly, what we're trying to be is as transparent as possible in terms of the work.
There are certain pieces of the work that we are able to continue forward on once the designs are complete. We have real concerns about any delays in terms of cost escalation in Hong Kong and the fact the longer these projects go, the more expensive they're likely to be. No, in regard to the
Specifics around M Plus. If we can resolve the the outstanding issue in regard to public infrastructure, then we're reasonably secure in the idea that we will be able to ensure Op by sometime early to mid eighteen.
And then, so that's going to be something we'll be spending an intense amount of time looking at over the course of the summer. I'll ask Dr. Nitford to just respond on the overseas programmes and the broader activity.
Okay， Mister。
No, it's on.
In terms of audiences, I don't have the total figure, but we can say that inflation attracted a bit over one hundred and fifty thousand visitors. The architecture exhibition about twenty thousand. Other exhibitions are around ten to fifteen, twenty thousand visitors. If you and of course then we have the neon.
科學項目，which attracted a couple of hundred thousand unique visits. Actually, three hundred thousand, I think it was roughly unique visits to the site, and a lot of also viewing of our YouTube film of making neon signs, and and more than four thousand individuals submitted images of neon signs, their favourite neon signs in.
香港，所以，我意思，如果你總結所有這些人，那些實際去的，我們在數字上超過200,000，如果我們加上當然數字的參與，就更多。在背景上，大多數都是去參觀展覽的人。我意思，我們有壓倒性的香港人參與。
At the same time, I think it's important to underline that M Plus status and standing internationally is extraordinary, and we have lots of requests for visits. Who wants to come and visit the museum because they believe that we're fully operational, up and running, because of the reporting on what.
What we're doing in the international media, and we have to disappoint people and say sorry. You can come to our office, but there is no museum to look at yet, and we don't happen to have a project up and running at the present. Okay,好，我，主席，主席，唔好意思啊，即係或者部分嘅數字，希望係畀畀我哋，即係話你延遲一個月。
會增加幾多費用呢啲嘅？我哋知道。我係very happy to provide statistics today。誒，副主席，係係多謝主席。誒，噉我諗咧，我哋應該為呢個M plus咧係受到誒世界各地嘅收藏家同埋咧時代藝術家嘅重視咧係噉。
感到高興啦，因為呢個亦都係我哋喺要建構呢一個西九文化藝術區，希望達到嘅目的就係再將香港咧擠翻喺國際嘅文化藝術嘅版圖上面，成為另一個亮點。咁至於而家咧，我哋係誒向緊呢個目標。
都要進發緊啊！
噉啊！我想問一問咧，就係喺誒。
嗰個培養本地嘅視覺藝術家嗰方面咧，究竟喺呢個M plus嗰個誒策展嘅？
誒策略啊，同埋咧嗰個誒安排咧，有啲乜嘢部署咧？因為我都係好希望香港有好多誒視覺藝術家咧，將來可以靠呢個平台咧，係進身國際嘅舞台咧，亦都係可以誒將佢哋嘅嗰個視覺藝術咧，係同世界各地嘅人。
分享嘅噉，所以我第一個問題係先問一問咧，就係對於培養啊本地嘅視覺藝術家係有乜嘢嘅具體嘅誒安排？第二個問題咧就係我想問下呢個成立一間全資附屬公司嚟都進行M Plus運作咧，係唔係？
係西九管理局，將來都會用一樣嘅模式套用於其他嘅展館、場館嗰度咧。啊，呢個係唔係就係體現啊？主席都知，我一直都講嘅藝術責任制嘅其中一個啊手段啊，呢個我想知道係咪適用於？
其他嘅場館。好，係Mr Lynch。Mr Chairman, I'll take the second question. It doesn't presuppose that we will have independent governance for each venue, and clearly that's an issue that we will be considering. But the important issue for M+, and that's why this decision.
has been discussed for many years, is that the the sense of independence, curatorial independence, and the ability to be able to raise funds to contribute to the collection, in addition to the support from government, will be clearly much more advantaged by the subsidiary model.
Clearly, having a board that is focused on M Plus rather than on all of the other issues, but with a direct relationship to West Kowloon, will be I think an important step in the evolution. It will put M Plus on a similar basis with other major contemporary art museums around the world, and we see that as a very
Very important step forward. In regard to the other venues, we're looking at both the timing issues as to when venues are going to be completed, and then what are the best governance and managerial models for taking it forward. But the only one that is immediately relevant to us.
alongside M Plus is the Z Shu model, which the Performing Arts Committee and the Board will be considering over the coming months. And I might ask Lars to just comment on your first point. 我就想跟跟呢個答案咧，就係邊位而家係會諗住做呢一個M Plus呢個全資扶助公司嘅董事。
局嘅主席啊！
Well, I think that their decisions made by the board and the government. The government appoints, you know, the members of the West Kalloon board, and clearly, you know, we don't have any say in those decisions.
好噉，關於個培養本土藝術家嗰度，啊，藝術多謝你。
Well, it's not directly the task of a museum, of course, to to sort of educate artists. That is done by universities and the art schools. Naturally, I think the role that a museum plays is already when you are in education, you offer the students.
Food for thought, things to look at. They get to know other artists and other developments and other movements. So that's the basis for it to stimulate them and inspire them and so forth. The next step is of course, and I think that's more what you are thinking of is of course, to what extent will we be a platform for for Hong Kong artists?
Of course, we will not be a platform for all Hong Kong artists. That is impossible, and I don't think that's that's the the task for us. But we will clearly be a platform for Hong Kong artists, just as any national museum and any other part of the world would be a platform for its artists, but also for
bringing artists from other parts of the world to Hong Kong for inspiration and excitement for the wider public and so forth. So I think that
M Plus could be a place where you know that you will be aiming at as an artist. It doesn't mean that you have to be old and have worked for thirty, fifty, thirty, forty years before you get a chance. But it's for the top talents, of course, of Hong Kong, and it's a great chance to make Hong Kong artists known.
To the wider public, we have seen from last year in Venice that if it's done right and if it's done with sort of the right backing, a Hong Kong artist who is relatively unknown beforehand can become an international name by just having the right backing and the right platform. And that's what we hope to provide.
By M Plus. Okay，誒多謝你，誒陳婉霞。
同樣行到嚟，唔該，我聽唔到，冇事。誒，主席，其實我都係跟進翻呢個問題嘅。
嗱，我對於誒即係要成立一個全資嘅附屬嘅管理，咁咧我自己誒同啲誒西九啲朋友都問呢個問題。
我點解做一個噉嘅船資啊？如果按照剛才嘅解釋就話，哦，我為咗佢更靈活同國際好多嘅接觸，噉我覺得如果咁講法，係咪我哋而家現有嘅架構係唔足夠呢點咧？
如果假如你話誒用呢啲理由嚟講咧，噉你將來可唔可以成立一啲戲曲中心公司咧、音樂中心公司咧？即係我覺得係咪各都有個平台咧？咁當時誒著個董事局管唔管到佢哋咧？佢哋可唔可可能成為一個獨立王國咧？呢個我擔心主席，即係我覺得我認同係需要同國際好多。
方面有好多聯繫啊、接軌啊等等，包括人才，但咁唔係一個理由要成立一個噉嘅全資獨立公司。我係好擔心到時成為一個獨立王宮點算咧？成個政府即係民政嗰度點去處理問題咧？我我都想問下，即係誒呢個部分誒應該由翻民政嘅官員答答我，即係你當。
佢哋提咗建議，你點睇咧？唔該曬主席。好啊，民政局答一答點樣？你點樣將來點樣去控制同埋監管呢啲公司？
多謝主席。誒，我哋都係贊同呢個建議嘅，因為咧，我哋覺得都係同國際嘅誒博物館去接軌啦。另外咧，雖然Ample將來會係一個全資嘅附屬公司啦，但係其實佢嘅人事啦、佢嘅財政計劃啦、佢嘅業務計劃咧，仍然係需要誒得到西九嘅管理局去批准嘅。
亦都係誒，佢其他嘅政策，譬如係。
誒人事、財政啊、I T啊、其他啊嘅政策咧，都係要跟翻誒西九管理局所定下嘅政策嘅。咁所以我覺得咧，誒個管理局誒西九管理局將來仍係會有足夠嘅誒誒監管嘅。喂，而家佢唔係全資嘅咧咩？而家西九管理局都全資㗎啦，全部都係獨立㗎啦。噉你點解？
全資獨立之下又全資獨立嘅咧，餵你噉樣一路噉樣。
Square上去唔掂㗎喎，噉你佢佢嗰個團體公司係咪淨係受西九管理局監管就唔需要將來使幾多錢做咩嘢，唔需要嚟立法會咧？因為係噉樣去架空立法會咧。主席，好似係我問啊，你記得。係啊，我我即係補充你個問題。你畀啲時間。你答清楚畀阿陳婉嫻啦。OK。
你覺得呢個好咩？即係而家你覺得呢個好？你你搭我哋先得㗎啊！OK。
誒，答唔答到啊？答唔到啊？Who do you want to answer？好多，我都仍然唔希望政府。佢問政府，佢問政府。好，政府嘅。呢個權係政府嘅嘛？唔該。係啊，你應該批唔批准個？你要講嘅嘛。我哋唔反對嗰個全資依誒附屬公司誒。噉你要達到。
嗰個陳陳議員講點樣將來點樣去監管，會唔會成為獨立王國？佢其實咧，佢其實唔會嘅，因為咧誒誒，將來emphas佢嗰個我財政預算咧，仍然係需要係得到我西九管理局好嘅誒批核嘅，而係誒整體嚟講咧。主席啊，如果
既然假如咁誒誒政府咁答咧，就何需有個全資獨立咧？即係你都係擴粗住佢哋嘅，佢只不過一班藝術家，你擴粗住誒嗰五指山鼠咧，舞嚟舞去佢咁咁有乜意思？我唔係好明喎。而家已經係全資㗎啦，而家已經係獨立㗎啦。即係我覺得奇怪啊！嗱，我尊重外行唔能夠誒管。
內行嘅嘢，我尊重呢點嘅。但問題就話你而家講係個好矛盾。我跟住問你噉，你其他啲係咪胎組啲音樂中心公司啊？誒，氣功中心公司係噉，全部都噉樣啊？咁將來如果有事咧，就主席佢就嗱，唔係我呢屆下屆，或者再下一屆就我唔關事。當時上屆上屆議會同意咗我做一個獨立公司，佢全部理曬。
咁到時我領唔到啊啊！無辦證咁先精彩喎，你你明我意思嘛？I think I answered that question already. The issue is M plus is a particular instance. I think you asked us a question at our last meeting about why a respected Hong Kong philanthropist had given a hundred million to the Asia.
Because he and the answer was because he perceived it to be an independent institution. Clearly, the fundraising capacity of M is a specific issue in in being able to build the collection and to build the philanthropic support in addition to the support that they get through the business planning process. But as I have.
誒我想講咧，and and it is absolutely clear from the existing structure and the existing ordinance that you know the Westcalle
文化局是那裡，能處理那啲問題。就係文化局嘅職能。
啊啊啊！陳我知嘅陳月陽，因為咧，我之前同過係啊，陳月陽都夠鐘啦，好嘛？不過你用咗我啲時間，我先用翻少少啫。我已經畀多咗你好多啦。OK，不過我想認睇，我認睇翻少少就話，我覺得政府如果你放權畀咗佢哋咧，我唔反對，但係我畀做個全資咧。
我好擔心到時可以做個平台拍賣啲古物古跡都得嘅，主席唔該。O.K.明白，我話呢個咧噉嘅情況底下咧，我諗咧你頭先一開始答啊副主席，我冇叫你講啊。Mr Lynch stop，等我叫你講你先講。頭先咧副主席就係。
講呢個問題，陳宇陽講一個問題。噉你可唔可以做一份文件？政府做一份文件翻嚟話畀我聽。有有咩機構？你已經話咗唔係所有機構都係用呢個方法嘅。噉你講各種嘅方法有咩好處唔好處？點解Amicus要用呢個方法？佢有咩特色？點解要用呢個方法？係。
同其他唔同，我知道你嗰個誒，即係唔係你做份文件答我哋得㗎啦，而家唔需要答嘛，多謝下一位，我收啦。
係啊，主席，我我第一我要多謝誒管理局誒揾到咁多捐贈啦，即係包括係誒一啲誒藝術收藏品同埋誒金錢上嘅捐贈。咁呢個係誒即係要多謝大家係做得好好。第二咧就係嗰個誒。
誒，Amplus嘅內部同埋外部嗱，外部嗰個設計咧，噉我哋見過啦。但係我自己咧就覺得一個博物館咧，嗰個內部係即係又是展覽嗰部分咧，係比外外邊嗰個外觀係更加緊要嘅，因為裏邊要有誒彈性啦，令到誒。
誒，即係你做不同嘅展覽嘅時候，係可以即係誒誒適合到誒嗰某個展覽啦。咁而誒參觀嘅人咧，亦都係佢由踏入博物館個刻開始，佢點樣行誒？你嗰條路點樣設計，令到佢成個。
我誒睇展覽嘅經驗係誒有有一個互動喺度咧，咁呢呢個係好重要嘅。咁所以我希望就可以盡快畀我哋睇到誒內部嘅設設計，就唔係淨係外觀添啦。咁第三咧就係跟進啊，黃碧雲議員頭先講嗰個話誒。
即係要有翻一個誒老香港嘅誒誒影像擺喺度，等參觀嘅市民咧係可以睇埋一啲本土嘅文化。噉就誒，我頭先聽到誒誒就話即係施南生都可以幫手啦，即係揾一啲紀錄片。但係其實如果有施南生幫手咧，就應該揾佢。
即係誒睇翻香港嘅舊電影，因為裏邊咧係有不少嘅片段咧，都係好多香港嘅街景，噉就誒嗰啲其實都係好珍貴，但係可能就要同誒電影資料館嗰度大家合作，即係做一啲剪輯，噉我係希望誒Ample嘅團隊係可以幫手做到呢個，到最後咧都真係要問翻個。
管治架構，因為喺第十五段嗰度咧，噉佢嗰個起始咧，就係話為咗消除同博物館有業務來往人士眼中法律上不明確之處，噉我就好想問。
究竟呢啲業務往來人士究竟係乜嘢人咧？同埋佢哋眼中嘅法律不明確之處係乜嘢不明確咧？因為我哋要知道咗個原因，然後先知道即係呢個解決方法係咪即係最有效啊嘛。咁所以就誒，主席我就想畀我剩翻一分鐘嘅時間，就畀誒。
誒，Mr Michael Lynch去講誒，佢佢頭先想解釋嘅嘢咯。好啊，Mr Lynch。
Thanks, Mr. Chairman. I guess the issue of and the idea of the importance of being able for the for the museum to be able to run a program, to be able to pick up and and take exhibitions to other museums, for other museums to bring exhibitions to this museum, is.
An important part of the business of contemporary art museums, the importance of independence of both curatorial direction is an important part of it. But I think as important in terms of the proposed governance structure is the idea that the outside world, the people who want to support the museum.
in either donating works to the museum, donating money to the museum, that they want to see that it is a museum and that it operates on the same basis that other museums operate around the world, and it's not a private museum, it's a not-for-profit institution.
Clearly needs and it is the only visual arts organisation within West Kalim. So the justification for it being having a different governance structure than the fifteen theatres in West Kalim and a range of the other facilities has, I think, been strongly argued.
Over the last seven or eight years, pre the establishment of West Kowloon, these issues have been canvassed. They've come out of the Hong Kong visual arts community, and I think there is a strong in principle support for establishing this museum on a different basis to the existing not for profit.
Government institutions in Hong Kong, and we see significant benefits from that structural situation, while recognising that there is still a very close relationship between M+ and the rest of the West Kowloon Board, the West Kowloon Organisation, and is a critical part.
The West Kowloon site. Okay, thank you, Mo Banting.
各位主席，Mr Lynch， you have to understand our concern about M+ being an independent institution.
Is it going to become? Well, just could I clarify? I don't actually clearly understand. Bearing in mind the issues that you know we have continually discussed, I would be glad. Can I, Mr. Lynch? Mr. Lynch，你讓嗰啲議員問曬問題你先答啦。你兩個喺度對話嘅時候，我都唔知你哋做緊乜嘢，好嘛？請你。
Right, the fact that it just might become a little empire.
啊，Beyond， what about funding applications in the future? As the chairman was asking earlier, would it need to go through Olegco at all? You would only come under the authority, right? So we're not too sure about the entire setup. That's a problem. That I'll give you plenty of time to.
回應到這個問題，和我的第二個問題是：，看那張特別的幻燈片，從M+從公園看。
It doesn't look very impressive, I have to say. Maybe, well, I'm not an artist in any way. But then, from layman' viewpoint, I was actually looking forward to some sort of landmark, and I was particularly almost baffled by the design that it actually.
sit right in front of a building behind.
Is that what it's about? I thought that's an architectural crime almost. What's that about? Could you tell us more? Two questions, thanks. To your second question, no, we sit on a forty hectare site in front of some of the less attractive and less impressive architectural offerings in Hong.
Hong Kong and no, that's the reality of life. No, I don't think we can take responsibility for what's been built around the rest of the West Kowloon site. I disagree with you in principle, and and we've clearly argued the merits. No, we've gone through competitions. We've had the best architects in the world.
主席啊，即係而家嗰設計事實係好似一個箱噉樣咯，就唔真係唔係特別啊？覺得唔係啊，Mr. Lynch，你畀佢講完先，我叫你答你先答啦。而家係開緊會。啊，都轉啊，你慢啲咩？OK，Mr. Lynch，your terms。
I think we are, and clearly the response from Hong Kong, from the rest of the world to the the winning design and the proposal as the design has developed is very positive. Clearly, I guess plenty of people I know members of the the committee have.
Their views about that. We will robustly engage with you on why this decision was made. So on that part of it, I guess we just have to agree to differ with the committee. In regard to independent, there is no the idea of the ongoing.
locus of this committee, whether it be on M plus or on any other of the parts of the West Kowloon project, is very clear. No, we would like this committee to assist us in being able to move forward some of the things that, particularly at the moment, endanger the progress on the project. But we
It doesn't matter what the appropriate governance arrangements that are decided for M+ and for the rest of the site. It will still be under the scrutiny of the Legco, and if this committee continues, we assume of this committee. And now, in terms of the funding.
proposals and the funding base. Some of the money will come from the West Kaluan Authority in the formal process of submitting a business plan and being approved by the West Kaluan Board, which is then comes to the Ledgeco. Clearly, what we are also trying to do is to diversify.
的 funding base to be able to encourage collections, to be able to encourage philanthropy and other support, which ensures that the citizens of Hong Kong are paying less for the the future of the project, and we are maximising the possibilities of of other support。好多謝你嚇噉。
噉啊！最後我就有啲問題，即係我想即係代表咧政府好西九咧，即係你哋嘅文件已經畀咗我哋睇嘅啦，唔需要再讀多次。用咗廿五分鐘去讀咧，其實都解決唔到即係議委員對你嘅問題。但係你對呢個西九呢個設計咧，你係用三張圖就咁簡單講，所以我。
我都同同意阿毛孟靜嗰個睇法。你根本我就去睇過你哋嘅展覽，但係你都解解釋唔到點解你由共五個會揀依個？依個佢有咩特色？佢係嗰個內涵係講乜嘢？佢係表代表啲咩嘢？即係當香港市民又好，外地人嘅嚟又好，喂，依個係乜嘢嚟㗎？即係你。
解釋唔到依個佢一個象徵啲乜嘢，或者佢想表達啲咩嘢，只不過見到一個好大嘅巨型嘅建築物啊，打環好似屏風樓噉，又或者大電視機，即係之前講或者倒轉嘅嘅三號風球嗰個曬咁變咗，即係大家都覺得錢啊用得好多。
之前你話四啊七億，而家變咗五啊幾億，即係你依個咁用咗咁多錢，即係差唔多每尺咧超過五萬蚊嘅呢個建築費。
噉你用咁多錢去起呢個咁大嘅白象？
但係你又講唔到內涵，即係一個冇靈魂嘅白象，咁所以我覺得即係好失望。今次你根本喺度解釋就唔得。第二咧，喺你個軟件嗰方面咧，你個購藏政策你都未曾話畀我哋聽。喂，究竟你個定位點咧？你個Amper嘅定位係乜嘢？
你想係喺世界上定啲咩位？喺亞洲上定咩位？香港你點樣定位？你都定唔到個位。噉你如果定到個位，你知你先有個構長構長方向。你點樣去去達到呢構長方向？用咩方法？但係你冇，你只今次你啊有解釋到啦。你就話留翻畀成立嗰個獨立公司。
全之嗰個公司去諗咯，噉樣喂咁唔得㗎喎。好似頭先有啲委員咧就話：喂，你而家應該有依個方向㗎嘛，係嘛？如果你而家都冇方向嘅，噉你而家做乜嘢咧？將來再揾人去去做噉，我噉你點解而家要買咁多嘢咧？買個嘢，依啲嘢係咪係係？
滿足或者你接收人哋嘅贈品嘅時候，你係咪滿足你呢個方向咧？你而家冇喎，冇方向，即係將啲有有嘢你去買啊靚嘢又買，你認為靚啦，我哋都未必認為靚。但係有誒有人送你又收，其實係一個好似打亂仗咁亂亂糟糟噉樣。噉你覺得你點樣去去詳細去解釋你？
呢個政策，噉啊最後一點咧，就好多同事咧，都係好多委員都提過咧。你成立一個傳捷公公司咧，有冇噉嘅必要？點解要傳做喺Amperes要咁做，喺其他嘅場館唔係咁做？
可唔好咧？喺依三個問題咧，你都係希望你能夠咧喺文字上詳細向我哋解釋，將來討論好嘛？多謝嚇。O.K.，Mr. Lynch。
Well, in regard to your third third part of your question, as I've said repeatedly today, we have not the nature of a of a major museum on which we spend five billion dollars has different requirements than the individual theatres that we're building on the.
其他parts of the site. That's part of the justification in terms of what we're talking about with the governance model. Clearly, I don't entirely understand your comments in regard to the collection. There is an acquisition policy which is publicly available. We have provided information on all of the acquisitions.
That we've made both to this committee and online and in various other forms and responses, and that's we understand the ongoing need to explain what's in the collection and how the collection's done. Any donation to the collection goes through the same.
如果你唔明白咧，我會plan威噉樣寫畀你。我就覺得你嗰個，我。
Your question, Mr. Chairman, I just don't think you're allowing me an opportunity to answer your question. And and in regard to your first question, no, I think the issue, no, the reality of life is that no more than a year ago the government announced the winner of the competition for M+ announced the budget. We are in
line with the budget， we are in line with the design process。唔係，我明白。從那點嘅觀點，我會在誒文字上講清楚問啲咩問題，好嘛？無謂嘥時間，因為我哋仲有一part咧都好重要。我哋進入第二part咧，就係關於個公園最新嘅發展同埋設計用途同埋管理。噉我哋希
希望用誒五十分鐘嘅時間去講咁誒，邊位答誒？邊位會介紹一下？
係，啊。
I will, Mr. Chairman.
Clearly, the park is probably the most anticipated facility of the West Kowloon Cultural District. You are well aware, as members of the committee, of the decisions that were made last year when some of the changes were outlined by the chairman in June last year.
We clearly see the park is not only a major green space in the heart of the city, but a very important part of what we're trying to do to inspire, promote and encourage cultural pursuits for all. And we've strongly reiterated the issue of the park as all of
West Kalume will be a place for everyone. As we set out in our discussion paper, we've been moving very quickly on a number of fronts. In February this year, we appointed the park design team, and that park design team is comprised of Dennis Lau and Ung Chun Man Architects.
And ACLA from Hong Kong and Westgate from Rotterdam in the Netherlands, one of the world's leading park designers. And today we have Martin Biwenga from Westgate and Chung Kwong Wing from Dennis Law to be able to take you through where that design now is.
And in terms of the key issues that have been raised by members of the committee over, I think I would say over the last two years, on park use and management, as we mentioned to members at the June meeting, we have just completed the engagement exercise led by the consultation panel to.
Collect public views on how the park should operate. That exercise is now completed, and we had shared with members some of the preliminary findings. In we also, beginning now as we move towards the resolution of the park, we now are talking about.
如何的公園是將要被管理，和總體框架的公園條例。我們非常清楚地對聽見成員的觀點。一旦我們能夠概述今天這個提案，我想這是我的起點。我現在想介紹馬汀。
Bwenga from Westde to take us through a quick run through of what is a quite complex development. So I hope the committee will give us the opportunity to be able to take you through the key issues.好啊，誒，多歡迎你兩位出席啊。噉啊，請你用十五分鐘嘅時間介紹啊，你哋嘅。
係。
睇啲咩先啊？
My name is.
我哋聽到㗎啦。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
My name is Martin Biwenga.
Director of Westade Landscape Architects.
We are designing and building parks around the world in New York, Madrid, Toronto, and now in in Hong Kong, which is a very exciting opportunity for us.
We work with a very strong local team for a good implementation of the design.
和。
The park. Today, we would like to share with you the concept design for the for the park.
In our view, the park will be a tranquil and sublime counterpoint to the intensity of of Hong Kong city.
一 Place where residents can go to relax and enjoy the green space and the waterfront.
We think the park will be a magnet for people, for families, but also for visitors with the new Kaloon station.
和。
Interestingly, the the park has a a second identity.
which is an active identity.
誒。
Because it can accommodate events, festivals.
Performances, but also food and and art.
Because the park is designed, of course, as a as being a part of the cultural district of of Hong Kong.
On the screen, you can see the the plan of the concept design.
with clearly the the entrance to the West Kaloon crossing.
and also of course on the right side here, the M+ museum, the artist square and the
the start of the avenue.
of the West Kaloon Cultural District.
在公園，整合在設計的係兩個通風建築。
That at the moment, of course, since the site is empty, are very prominent.
on the on the side the ventilation building for the highway tunnel and the and the MRT.
啲。
backbone of the park.
是個是個行人步道，係基本上係一條延伸的街道，從未來的文化區、文化區的西九龍。
which continues across the across the artist square into the park, let's say descending down into the park and being the major archery of the of the park for pedestrians.
And let's say as a as an anchor point for cultural activities in the park.
This is an impression we made from the cultural boulevard.
印象從。
And plus descending down into the park, giving visitors beautiful vistas through the park.
on on the waterfront of Hong Kong, on the other side of Victoria Harbour.
The park itself is an interesting hybrid of of of green space.
Of a green leisure space for for for local residents and for Hong Kong residents.
Combined with performance spaces, performance venues.
exhibition spaces here on the top left.
你睇啲設計， for the art pavilion， which is located in the park。
But also cafes and and small restaurants in the park to to make make it a comfortable visit for the for the people.
Next to the cultural boulevard, the second, of course, main attraction of the park is its.
是啲可達性到水邊。
嗯。
The park has a 1.2 kilometre public waterfront.
一promenade that is that provides 270 degrees views to Victoria Harbour and Hong Kong Island and to the to the west.
very spectacular. This is something that is given to the site, and we are using it in the in the design.
especially the southern part of the of the waterfront promenade is widened to create a larger space.
To allow large groups of people to enjoy the beautiful view on on Hong Kong Island.
這些係一些，let's say，初始 renderings  from this space on the waterfront。
It's a mix between a square and and a lawn.
Providing access to the to the waterfront.
和。
What is very important in design and important to understand is that, since the park will be a mix of event spaces and park spaces, we think it's very important that if there is an event in the park.
people can still use the the rest of the park for leisure.
所以，the park will not be shut down if there is an event. You can still use the park, and for that reason, we introduced.
especially on the southern edge.
An elevated park edge, you can see that here in the section.
所以，如果係一個事件喺水front。
誒。
The users of the park can still enjoy the the views over the over Victoria Harbour. We think that's a very important element of the of the park design.
這是一個印象， of that waterfront space.
with a wide pedestrian boulevard.
alone with a cycle track， running through it。
and the the edge the double edge, where people can enjoy the waterfront in the shadow of the of the edge, but also on the
On the elevated level here, which is also a promenade with the park on top.
the the space between the cultural boulevard and the waterfront.
是個proper park。
That can accommodate cultural events and art events.
as an as an extension as a natural extension of the West West Kaluan Cultural District.
We've accommodated different spaces in the park for small and larger events.
One of the main areas for large events will be the big lawn.
the the light green space, which is a which is a an open space in the park that can accommodate more than ten thousand.
Visitors for large-scale outdoor events.
Of course, there is this this space on the waterfront.
for for events that that that use the the magnificent views.
在心臟的公園是個更親密的公園區域。
of which we think that that is a very interesting area for families and for for local visitors.
And of course, there is an area in the park which is adjacent to the to the M+ museum. It's a lawn that is that is sloping down into gently gently sloping down into the park.
We've tested the activities that have been organised by West Kaluan Cultural District in the past on the park design, and we are comfortable that these activities can take place in the in the future park.
Some of the activities are large, attract a lot of people. Some activities are smaller, and the park can accommodate both type of cultural activities.
In this rather technical plan, you can see the different.
exhibition spaces， the big lawn。
the smaller lawn for more intimate events and intimate activities, the waterfront plaza event space and the lawn related next to M+ and of course in the northern part of the park the temporary
temporary event space which is already in place and is already used intensively.
From the Cultural Boulevard, we've created different connections through the park, pedestrian connections to the waterfront.
The connections are not only physical connections, but also let's say guide the views from the visitors to the to the waterfront.
Here's an overview of the park.
with the in the heart of the park, the black box theatre.
With cafes around it and the art pavilion adjacent to it, the art pavilion will be one of the first initiatives in the park.
散佈在公園內的有各種休憩設施，例如咖啡館、餐飲店，當然還有公廁，讓遊客在公園內可以更舒適地遊覽。
This is a view from the big lawn.
where we let's say simulated the festival. The festival is a is a outdoor stage that is related to the black box theatre, so it can utilise the facilities of the black box theatre.
And the lawn is a place where people can sit on the grass, but also enjoy the shadow of the surrounding tree lines.
And the lawn basically borrows the view from M+ here in the back, and of course the West Kowloon Cultural District will develop.
Its skyline in the back of this of this view.
The small one is a is a much more intimate space, with a.
with a intimate character, very much suitable for small exhibitions and for families to enjoy enjoy the park.
In a in a shaded in a shaded condition.
Of course, what is not part of the design but is is a given from the site, is that it is unprecedented in its in its spectacular view.
And the design completely celebrates this.
這些 views on the skyline， 我們有 270 度。
views over the harbour.
and especially the waterfront.
Event space let's say celebrates the view on on Victoria Harbour and and Hong Kong Island.
We've tested this space for different events and it's a very flexible space that can accommodate different events.
This is an important image because, of course, the M Plus Museum is facing on to the park.
And this is a view from the botanical garden into in the park.
where you see the lawn and the M+ museum in the back.
啲。
We think that let's say the the art component of the park can be quite important.
In curating pieces for the park, public art displayed in the park, and we've pointed out different places where we think permanent or temporary art installations can be accommodated in the park and surprise and.
And welcome the visitors to the park.
Very important element of the park, and that is that has already been initiated by West Kaluan Cultural District, is a is a bicycle programme.
Along the waterfront, we've accommodated a bicycle route network that where visitors can cycle along the waterfront, and of course this route anticipate on future connections to the city of.
卡隆。
The botanical aspect of the park has two main ingredients.
We think, and especially if you compare the design with the current situation where it's very empty and flat, it's very important to provide shading for the visitors because it Hong Kong has a hot climate.
所以，一大 part of the trees that will be planted have the function of providing shadow.
And the rest of the trees are very much there to experience the different seasons. So the autumn and the spring. So these are very much flowering trees.
as you can see here on the
on the slides.
Along the main footpath in the park, we will have the the trees to provide the shadow for the visitors, and we combine that with small pavilions, shading structures.
作為 resting points along the route， and to give shadow and protect from from rain.
At the moment, since the site is a landfill, it's very flat, and what we've done is introduce topography on the site.
to create spectacular views over Victoria Harbour, to connect the park with the surrounding areas of M+
And also to manage rainwater in a sustainable and ecological way in the in the park.
So, as a conclusion, we think that the the concept design for the park is an interesting hybrid between a local park and that can accommodate events in the in the cultural district of West Kaloum.
Thank you very much。好，多謝你嚇，係。
冇補充啦。如果冇補充，我哋就委員提問嘅時間。一咧排咗隊有範國威誒副主席，即係委傳，噉我。
每人四分鐘，連問連答。
請凡各位。我對主席，我我想有幾個問題問嘅。如果問唔曬，我留第二輪啦。第一個問題咧就係喺誒，未必有第二輪啊，儘量咩咩話？未必有第二輪，儘量揾得精簡。誒，第一個問題咧就我想問喺成個公園，因為都係即係其中一個好重要嘅部分啦。誒，我睇文件，我唔知有冇睇漏咧，就喺呢。
一個嘅西北邊嗰度仲有一大塊，即係都係應該係有草皮地，亦都係公園嘅一部分，係咪因為工程上面嘅需要、office嘅需要，又或者有一度話咩plan leisure，即係逐時嘅追需要，所以唔係同步地係去做規劃，呢個第一個嘅問題啦。如果唔係話咧，應該同步去做嘅話咧，嗰度佔地一啲都唔。
少嘅噉樣。第二個問題咧就係誒誒，我知道咧就話希望。
喺整個公園裏邊咧，將綠化嘅範圍就最擴大，即係好maximum maxim呢一個即係綠化地方。咁裏邊咧有兩個建築物就冇得搬走，亦都唔係公園原有嘅，即係呢個西隧嘅通風大樓啦，同埋呢個港鐵嘅通風大樓。記住，港鐵啊，唔係地鐵。零七年之後冇咗地鐵㗎啦，港鐵通風大樓。
呢兩個誒，我見圖片嗰度咧，無論你個PowerPoint嘅第十五頁咧，好似佢佔地嘅地方，比如而家真實嘅情況，即係嗰啲石屎紅毛泥嘅地嘅位置，仲比而家係多咗，係咪已經係減到最少咧？誒，仲可唔可以喺誒令到佢可以整合同個範圍，可以即係更加多嘅？
綠化，例如係垂直綠化，又或者根本佢已經本身已經係好未來主義，好futuristic嘅，好似包house噉樣。你已經用啲好鮮黃啊、鮮藍嗰啲顏色，係令到佢都可以即係即係作為一個嘅誒建築設計嘅一部分噉樣。我係想問，即係如何地去整合嘅啫？第三咧誒建。
建築公司啊，West Eight係咪啊？啊，West八嗰度咧就誒有好多其他出名嘅國際設計喺設計上面特色上邊，即係你哋有提到New York嘅Governor Island Park啊、Miami嘅Lincoln Park，又或者係韓國首爾嘅龍山公園啊。喺嗰個特色上邊誒，有冇即係可唔可以畀多少少資料我哋？
有邊啲地方係相類似，有邊啲地方係我哋呢個嘅西九公園嘅特色係好unique嘅、好獨特嘅噉樣啦。係最後一個問題咧，就係誒有一個零一號文件，即係有好多嘅團體同埋啊市民比嘅就係個主題，就話叫當代方向，讓公眾或。
讓公民真正擁有西九公園，我想問佢哋畀咗呢啲意見裏邊，其實提好多即係公民係去參與啊。如何地影響誒西九管理局將會喺二零一五年年初交嚟我哋立法會有關嗰個附例嘅草稿，即係喺管理上面，你哋聽咗呢啲意見，佢哋提咗好多意見嘅，有啲我唔知道點樣具體地係去執。
憑嘅添，如何地令到公園嘅規嘅嘅限制係即係施加得最少，即係作為一個嘅大原則。有邊啲意見，你哋認為係可以吸納得到？即係佢哋有提到，即係公園附近有啲範圍用嚟釣魚嘅添噉樣係。咁呢啲係咪都係你哋會參考嘅咧？噉樣係主席四個意見，唔係四個問題。O.K.
Could I just deal with the first one, Mr. Fan? The site to the north of the park is the present temporary nursery, which will become a temporary park over the course of the coming year. We want to open that up for ongoing use. It is also the site for
The major perform performance venue, and and from that point of view, we don't know the timetable or when that's likely to be resolved. And then those two buildings that the are one of them is the project site office for the whole of West Kaloon, where we have half of our staff.
working on that in that building on the next to the tunnel, and then the rest of that site is existing ongoing use that will keep operating. Ultimately, once those decisions are resolved, once the rest of the park is done, we'd be then looking at extending the park.
Into that extra area, I might just ask Martin to make a quick comment on the issues you've raised about greening. We would very much prefer not to have the the two existing structures there, but we have very little control over them. It is very difficult to even.
disguise them. We've tried to to think of painting them, greening them, doing all sorts of things. But Martin may have a specific response to your question.
yeah the the two buildings are
That's very prominent in the in the current site. Also, their architecture is very explicit.
誒。
Of course, like you mentioned, the area around it's not only the buildings, but they also have service yards and and EVA access.
We're we're talking to the to owners to minimise the impact of the especially of the service yard.
And the let's say our approach to integrating these two buildings in the park is by hiding them as much as possible from the visitors by providing a green collar around them with trees and planting.
所以，especially when you're in the park, you will hardly notice the two buildings. Of course, if you are on the Hong Kong side and you look towards the park, because the buildings are so tall, you cannot miss them.
嗯。
When I compare the park to other designs, I think one of the
similarities is that and that's a general principle of landscape architect. You try to create and to to simulate nature by focusing, by guiding vistas, by creating distances.我諗時間夠啦，我一陣間會畀時間你再答，因為我都有相同嘅問題。下一位。
係副主席，係多謝主席。誒，首先咧，我諗要誒感謝阿Mr Martin Baique啦。
誒同埋West Eight咧，我諗誒初步噉樣，我睇你嘅介紹咧，就呢一個設計咧，的確係有好多誒，起碼我去過嘅比較靚嘅世界各地嘅公園啊嘅一個影子喺度。
誒，但係我就想集中個問題就唔係問West Egg嘅，我就想問下關於嗰個。
誒公園點樣管理嘅問題，因為呢個官呢個公園咧，無論係點樣美輪美換咧，誒，如果你用康文處嗰啲噉嘅。
公園副例嚟管咧，就肯定死梗嘅啊！咁所以咧，我啊想問下嗱，因為我喺文件度咧特別留意到誒第六段咧就有提到誒公園嘅定位啊、願景、使命咧，同埋咧就喺第二十二段開始咧就有交代到嗰個誒。
誒。
而家做緊嘅公眾意見調查嘅，我想問一問誒管理當局啦。即係呢一個願景同使命咧，就會係會進一步去誒討論之後去深化係嘛？因為你而家噉樣寫。
嘅願景同使命咧，就都係比較簡單。
噉啊，簡單唔係一定唔好，但係我就覺得可以再豐富少少。誒，或者我先講咧，主席就係我其實同意咧，即係你係唔應該由嗰啲負例。
嗰度出發嘅，嗱應該先定咗個願景同使命先咧。呢個係我完全擁抱同埋支持嘅方向，因為你只有知道個願景同埋誒使命咧，你先至可以喺取捨之間，喺誒。
點樣去寫嗰啲誒管理嘅符例誒嘅時候咧，係有所拿捏啦，亦都知所恆止。咁所以我其實同意個願景同使命。
係應該先定，然後咧就去先開始寫嗰啲扶例嘅。但係我就想問下，究竟呢個願景同使命咧係仲會有啲乜嘢嘅誒？公眾嘅參與啊，或者其他持份者嘅參與，你先會定實嗰個願景同埋使命咧？
咁另外就請交代一下嗰個時間表，即係幾時呢一個公眾意見調查係會有報告交到出嚟咧？同埋有咗報告之後，同誒寫好附例可以交嚟立法會期間嗰個操作，又會包含啲乜嘢嘅元素咧？
主席，好啊！請大家答邊位答？
Well, we hope to have the report finalised by September, and then to be able to bring it back here as soon as possible. Clearly, the ongoing work on vision, mission has been very much part of the philosophy behind the development of the park. But we are also running those processes in.
In parallel, and I think the important issue in regard to both address, I think I didn't address Gary Fan's question about fishing and some of the other issues. Clearly, we are looking at encouraging as many uses, both cultural and leisure uses, as we can. The view from the government and from
我們自己已經輕觸，清楚條例法令，讓我們確保公共安全和安全的最佳利益。認可，這是一個大場地，有潛在危險區域，我們需要管理。
要被 able to recognise the balance between the activities that take place that are organised by people or organised by us, but we're we're really looking at light touch in terms of the bylaws, and so and I think it is very clear in terms of public response to date that people want to be able to do as many
things as possible to be able to do things not in an organised form and I guess striking the balance both in terms of what we bring back to Ledgego for discussion I think it's been very clear the view from Ledgego over almost the three years I've been here is that they want the park to be open to
everybody, they want it to not be like necessarily other parks in Hong Kong, and clearly we're very much moving in that direction. Okay,多謝你，謝謝你。
多謝主席。誒，當然咧，即係呢個文化公園係非常重要啦。因為其實成個西九嚟講咧，佢都佔地相當大。噉啊，亦都係即係一般即係市民可以即係較容易享用嘅。噉啊，我都好開心咧，即係喺個設計方面咧，有強調咗即係點樣藝術啊、文化同埋呢個公園嘅。
呢個結合喺呢方面咧，就即係多謝嗰啲設計團隊喺呢方面，即係用啲腦筋，即係噉樣。噉我其實同其他同事都好關注咧。其實因為有誒兩個，即係包括嗰個港鐵啊，嗰個通風大樓同埋嗰個西隧通風大樓，另外亦都係西隧嘅入口。
呢呢啲咧，即係喺我都希望喺個設計上咧，盡可能咧睇下佢哋可唔可以，即係盡可能有配合啦。如果唔係咧，只係即係頭先講啦，可能係一啲即係自己做，將佢誒圍咗啊等等，使到嗰個視野上係即係嗰個誒影響減到最低。咁呢個我諗已經係。
最低限度咧，咁都希望即係積極啲。反而我我誒，主席，我另外都關注咧，就係誒設計之外咧，就係話誒呢個公園咧。頭先講過畀鄉市民享用啊，噉樣咁喺嗰個即係係使用者行人嗰個暢達性嘅問題咧，喺個設計上咧係有冇考慮？因為
如果唔係，淨係睇個公園咧，冇睇嗰個暢達性咧。尤其是咧，成個西九文化個發展咧，個時間都好長嚇。噉啊，有一段時間咧，就係可能有啲工程做緊嘅喺附近，亦都最後當然啦，就係所有工程做完啦。喺呢方面，喺個設計方面咧，係誒有冇共一。
同考慮咧，主要呢個問題，郭主席兩個問題。
嗰個對嗰幾個，thanks, Mr. Jay. Clearly, accessibility, as I've mentioned before, is one of the four principles that underpin this project. We we clearly recognise the importance of you know 23 hectares of public space within the 40 hectares. You know, clearly the basement project and being able to bring people in.
Under the ground, away from cars, does up throw up interesting issues in terms of how particularly the disabled and the elderly are able to get to the space. And we're looking. We think one of the the real strong parts of the Westgate D L N proposal is that it.
它 enables us to have no forms of transport for people who are no mobility challenged to be able to get to every part of the park. I personally cannot get to parts of the park if I rely on walking to it at the present time. Clearly, we're looking at making sure that every
part of the park is available. If you're in a wheelchair, you know you walk with a stick, or you know you've got children in in prams. That is a very fundamental importance of the cultural boulevard and the hard landscape relative to the soft landscape. Clearly, also drop off points, the ability of being
able to you know to move people around the site is a really fundamental principle and we will know that will be in the next stage of evolution of both the design and the practical moving forward on the park we'll be providing that information to Edgecar. 哎，主席我其實除咗個公園本身嘅設計，其實就點樣去個公
公園咧，尤其是咧，大家都明白。而家就要去嗰度就都好複雜嘅，因為而家太多公園做緊。咁但係我相信公園完成之後咧，其實有段時間咧都有工程喺附近嘅。噉我希望喺個設計咧，嗰個暢達嗰個就係唔單止本身公園本身，即係你點樣去到公園嗰度咧。
而家而家即係我自己行嗰度咧，真係好好混亂嘅。講真嚇，咁當然我希望咧，隨住嗰啲工程越嚟越即係完成多咧，就會更加好啦。不過我都希望咧喺設計方面咧都考慮，即係唔單止公園本身點樣去呢個公園咧，其實都係需要注意嘅嚇。唔該，主席。我我諗你記住啦嚇。
下一位陳婉霞，多謝主席。誒，我兩個方面嘅。
誒一個誒對公園嘅設計咧，我唔咁快落定論，因為淨係睇個平面圖睇唔到嘢嘅。我就已經同左西九咧，我唔該做個模型，我睇清楚啲。
起碼我而家初步睇個公園，你哋好大啦。
阿謝燕，以我自己認識嘅芝加哥，我喺説聽管絃樂嘅時候咧，嗰幅草地非常之大。我今日問佢哋，佢話一點幾公頃，係好細。就我想講，咁但係呢個，咁但係呢個我哋先天不足，我哋本身個地方就咁多啦嚇。咁但係問題就係點樣喺個基礎上做得更加達到我哋好似你諮詢意見噉樣咧？我好。
我希望盡快畀到我睇啲模型先得，咁睇我覺得我唔能夠作一個評價，我亦都唔係話好同唔好，即係呢個我想提出。第二個咧，我就關心有關誒你哋將會做一個負例咧，我覺得需要嘅。
亦都你將個附例，你就話會喺明年嘅年初咧話畀我哋聽。我就希望你未拍板之前咧，都嚟我哋呢度諮詢下我哋先。因香港喺管理公園係個好壞嘅一啲經驗就有，即係圍住曬公園噴水池可以鎖住佢唔畀入嘅，即係呢個就香港嘅康民柱做嘅嘢。
噉啊，當中亦都有個私人做嘅芝連正院，亦都令到地區多人好多困擾。即係你過分管又唔得，但你太鬆又唔得。點樣先吸納咗人？其他好似例如我哋去去美國紐約嘅中央公園啊，等等啲都好靚，亦都舒服，啲人都行得好好咧。嗱，我覺得呢個係吸納你當咗你當咗有啲段數講係吸納係人哋經驗，我其。
攀住，當我哋個負利嘅時候咧，過熱唔得，過速唔得。點樣過程當中咧，去除香港而家現在由我哋嘅康文署做嘅公園管理嗰種噉嘅陋習咧？我成笑香港嘅公園係啲殖民地嘅嘅一個方法，全部圍住圍住圍住，你都唔好入去。我我係好討厭呢啲做法。
但點樣記者之間做得好咧？所以我就希望當苦例嚟嘅時候，我希望政府答我，提早先同我哋講講先，唔好你成個例之後咧，我唔係唔信民政呢邊啊！我始終對民政你管屬下嘅康樂有意見，我想講，你睇你摩士公園咧，五號公園笑話嚟嘅，我唔喺你講啦。咁所以我就建議政府你臨當去拍誒。
好似草業前咧都嚟嚟我哋度，我啲分堆話啲同事聽下，我我期盼住，當你一五年上負利前咧係畀我哋先知先，因為我哋真係香港嘅經驗唔係太好嘅經驗嚟嘅。咁當然香港有啲地方有好經驗嘅，我咁講又唔得嘅，有啲當然都好嘅。我想強調一樣嘢。
咁所以我想強調一樣，例如我琴日好悶，我上山頂去個日式公園，好正。
好好，有例如我去到誒香港公園，亦都正嘅，即係我我要肯定香港有啲好嘅，但問題有唔好嘅更多添，咁所以我建議即係政府係。
誒係啦。
誒，民政答答我能否係提早畀我聽？另外，亦都希望誒西九辦答答我，係咪畀啲模型我睇睇咧？我唔想淨睇平面，唔想快落話好唔好？唔該。好誒，民政誒誒，民政答。We're very happy to provide you with the models, and and also.
Just to say that clearly, you know, the evolving of the both the park fire laws and the management philosophy will be important parts of the public communication. We will keep parts of the site open as we develop it, and it partly addresses Mr. Shaw's question. Clearly, being able
To keep that northern part of the the site there from early in the piece will also give us a good way to be able to model, in a smaller sense, some of the issues once the more bigger section of the park is being completed.
O.K.民政民政打一陣。
多謝主席。誒，雖然即係立法會多數都會成立專責嘅小組委員會嚟嘅審議嗰個附例，但係如果我議員講又需要我哋同西九管理局當去去草擬咗個，其實都會攞嚟，就會攞嚟，就會攞嚟誒，諮詢大家嘅意見。唔該。嗯。OK。OK。
誒，下一位何在啦？
唔該，主席。誒個公園咧，即係其實本來西九就成個西九都係要嚟做公園嘅。咁誒誒，呢個構思即係當時都相當受歡迎。咁而家即係做咗誒一橛文化設施，噉我哋都都支持嘅。咁但係一個公園咧，亦都確實喺呢個文化區嗰度。
咧佢就唔係其他任何一個香港其他嘅公園係應該有一個誒發展文化、培育文化嘅使命喺裏邊咁誒，而裏邊嗰個佈局同埋管理都係重要嘅，即係佈局方面，我哋點樣平衡佢可以？
誒做到誒一部分同另一部分之間有別有洞天嘅感覺，可以好自然咁誒區隔開嚟，互不幹擾。但係另一方面又唔好擺曬誒，即係政治花槽喺度，就係要嚟阻住唔畀你即係大堆人即係羣集埋一齊，就係要擺好多。
磚啊，或者大花盆啊，喺度即係令到你只能夠小組小組咁誒喺度傾偈，咁呢啲我哋都係唔希望嘅，咁誒誒嗰個。
公園成個誒公共空間裏邊咧，係應該係可以讓唔同嘅活動都各色其色，咁而最緊要就係有機去生長，有機去管理。所以即係我我哋咧就誒真係高度推介誒，我哋立法會收到誒有二十個團體同埋誒。
二百幾位香港市民畀我哋嗰個意見書，噉佢裏邊咧，亦都係講咗有一啲香港以往康文署嘅附屬法例咧，其實係誒扼殺咗誒好多自由嘅活動，例如誒即係唔準玩樂器啊，誒誒又或者係。
即係你喺嗰度嘅活動咧，係一定不能夠有金錢交易啊！咁咁呢啲都。
即係唔唔係唔係一個最自由嘅管理公園嘅方法，噉我就希望管理局咧喺誒成個誒。
睇呢個公園嘅誒佈局同埋誒做扶麗嘅時候咧，都真係要廣納民意。誒普通市民你要徵詢啦，但係文化界佢哋誒有啲誒邊個形式嘅活動係能夠最上個公園嗰個佈局係如何？
能夠配合到嘅，誒同埋嗰個誒管治管治個管理個方面，係希望點樣鬆綁嘅？噉我都請管理局係要喺成個過程裏邊去誒，尤其徵詢文化界咯。唔該，主席。
O.K.，誒，阿Bonny。
嗯，係誒，多謝主席。嗯，想回答翻，其實回答翻頭先範議員提出嘅，同埋而家何議員提出嘅啦，就係其實即係喺嗰個誒，我哋下次你答咧，就答翻問問題個議員，因為你用咗佢嘅時間，佢又同我去投訴㗎啦。唔係係一樣啫，一樣嗰個問題，即係話點去嗯。
誒回響翻文化界，琴日你哋入咗嚟入法會嗰封信啊。噉我哋其實琴日已經，我啱啱見咗我哋個諮詢委員會嗰個專責小組咧，就係關於誒呢個engagement啦。噉就阿黃英琦喺度嘅，噉我哋已經係約咗咧，話佢會幫手咧係約誒。
嗯，即係誒簽有份簽署嗰封信嘅好多嗰啲藝術家咧，咁嚟一齊誒，連同我哋嘅誒設計師係一齊去睇翻呢個呢啲圖啦。我哋而家有一個設計圖喺度，就係等佢哋去畀意見，係點樣可以最好地運用。
呢一個公園。
係，咁即係嚇我。
好啦，誒，再冇補充。如果冇補充咧，我諗最後咧，我嘅意見咧就係話，我哋誒呢個公園咧就同頭先個Amper有啲唔同啊。呢個都係好明確定定咗位，有個定位。頭先嗰個就冇啊。咁呢個定位咧係主要係話，我哋設計師點樣去即係能夠達到。
去呢個願景同埋使命，呢佢哋嘅寫低出嚟嘅目的。
咁剛才介紹咧好好好好詳細啦，咁有廿幾個slide，但係咧我始終都係覺得咧，即係單憑睇個slide都唔夠，好似頭先有委員講咧，我哋希望咧誒遲啲咧就能夠有一個model咧出嚟，因為噉樣會清晰一啲，因為仲有啲問題都未解決，譬如話。
嗰個誒，即係可達性咧。譬如話，依個公園佢又冇一啲誒，依啲路咧，係咪每一處地方都可能咧？喺緊急嘅時候咧，有緊急車輛可以救援嘅時候咧，可以達到係可以好短時間咧，可以即係幫到一啲有需要嘅居民咧，係咧。咁依啲。
情況都係即係，除咗佢靚之外咧，你都要係有個嗰個誒實用啊，同埋方便到市民。咁其實呢個圖嘅設計咧，同原本forest嗰個設計咧有啲唔同嘅。即係forest嗰啲咧，成個森林咁好多好多好多樹，但係而家就冇咁多樹，但係呢啲樹。
唔緊要，你你噉樣設計都有你哋嘅概念，我覺得都尊重你嘅概念，但係。
誒，有冇考慮到香港嘅天氣咧，同埋呢個位置咧？香港有颱風。
如果打一場風，會唔會又全部冧曬？噉你又要去做過曬，咁會嗰個價錢係點咧？即係呢個唔係話發生唔啊冇可能發生嘅，因為香港周時我哋見到，尋日落一場大雨都有啲樹冧咗，咁變咗我哋喺呢個設計上邊點樣又係滿足到你個設計？
又可以應付到即係香港嘅天氣同埋呢塊地嗰個地理環境咧。噉我哋希望即係誒，即係西九管理局同埋設計師嗰邊咧去注意注意呢樣嘢。噉我哋期望著咧，你盡快可以即係畀到個即係設計嘅嘅模模型啦。第二咧。
關於嗰個拜羅嗰度咧，嗰個例咧，係咪即係希望咧不久將來咧都可以誒拎上嚟畀我哋睇？咁呢個就可以誒，即係同大家頭先講咧，我哋可以詳細啲講嗰個公園嘅管理嘅問題，因為而家講講個管理問題咧，就係係比較空泛一啲，好嘛？總言嚟講咧，我好多謝。
即係兩位設計師專程喺外地嚟香港同我哋解釋啦，嚇！噉我哋好多謝你嘅解釋。
嚇啊！你你仲有咩咧？誒好簡單一個問題啫。頭先啊，陳耀仁議員即係話希望有個模型。我講咗咯，我我知道。係咯，我想問，我想提第二樣啫。我想問而家即係設計師嗰邊咧，因為而家用C G即係模擬，用電腦模擬咧，其實都係普遍嘅。嗰個其實會即係喺嗰個。
嗰啲樹木啊，周遭嗰啲嘅建築物嘅比例嗰啲咧，係能夠更加可以協助得到我哋去visualize，即係去去想象或者係去理解嗰個具體嘅設計。呢度設計師嗰邊係咪都係會應用喺未來日子裏邊協助我哋啦，或者係西九管理局喺？
設計呢個公園嗰陣時係會應用得到，如果係嘅話咧，嗰啲資料畀我哋咧係會幫到好多好多嘅噉樣。我諗咧就畀唔畀我哋另外一件事啦，就係張總，你嘅意見好好嘅，我哋希望咧即係如果能夠誒做個模型出嚟之後咧，喺依個電子嘅模型裏邊咧都有一啲三維空間嘅電子模型。
畀我哋睇咯，每一個部羣嘅詳細嘅表演啦，好嘛？嚇，咁喺度咧，我哋都多謝，再次多謝大家。Have you seen anything?
我 just make one point in regard to the trees. Clearly, the discussion of climate and trees has been really important part of developing both the design. But your point, you know, is is very important. The nursery that we put in some eighteen months ago on the site has some fifteen hundred trees in it.
And although they've they've grown substantially over the period of time, part of the purpose behind the nursery, which will become the temporary park over the course of the next year, was to test the typhoon resistance of those trees. Clearly, we've had good response, and the view from Westgate and
The DLN team is that most of the trees that we had put in the nursery will be able to be used and will be able to be planted as they're developed。好啊，多謝你。噉我多謝你哋嘅出席。咁誒，我哋依個議題咧就誒完成。咁喺會議結束之前咧，我都想詢問下大家咧，因為
噉啊，頭先都仲有好多問題存在嚇，咁咧咪大家同意咧，我哋都寫信畀兩個panel咧，就係要求呢個小組咧喺下一個年度咧，我哋都係繼續去誒，即係繼續去開會，係進行我哋個工作。大家冇反對啊嘛，嚇有冇反對？
對咧，我哋就誒寫信畀有關嘅委員會，好嘛？好多謝大家。
好嘅。